Finding Aid for St. Peter's Evangelical Lutheran Church (Plymouth, Mich.) records, 1856-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Peter's Evangelical Lutheran Church (Plymouth, Mich.) records 1856-1985
St. Peter's Evangelical Lutheran Church (Plymouth, Mich.)
89507 Ba 2
Church organized in Plymouth, Michigan in 1856; congregational minute books, 1856-1947; board of stewardship minute books, 1959-1967; announcement books, 1931-1960; subject files relating to the church's history, its administration, buildings, pastors, and activities; church publications; visual materials; and sound recordings.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the church (donor no. 7578 ) in July 1988.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The congregation of the St. Peter's Evangelical Lutheran Church was first organized in Plymouth, Michigan on March 5, 1856 by Reverend Friedrich Schmid. In 1833 Schmid was sent by the Basel Mission Society in Switzerland to lead a congregation of German Lutherans in Ann Arbor, Michigan. As part of his ministry, Schmid regularly traveled to Plymouth to act as the spiritual leader for the few German Lutheran families located there. Having no formal church organization, Schmid held services in private homes on a rotating basis.
Not until 1856 did the Lutherans of Plymouth organize into a congregation. Five leading men within the German community agreed to become charter members of the church. These men were Peter Gayde, J.M. Petershans, Peter Trinkaus, Johann Georg Fischer and Wilhelm Amrhein. Schmid himself was elected president.
On March 11, 1856 the congregation purchased its first church building from the local Baptist congregation for $140.00. Additional costs included the purchasing of a new site upon which to locate the church, moving the building to the new site, and preparing it for use. When the church had been paid for in its entirety, it was dedicated on December 26, 1858. Much financial hardship was experienced as the congregation endeavored to generate the necessary funds to maintain the church and its congregation through the period of the Civil War and the attendant postwar depression.
Having survived the economic depression from 1867 to 1879, the fortunes of St. Peter's congregation improved. Under the leadership of Pastor H. Abelman, the voting members decided to build a new church (referred to in the finding aid as "Old Church" since the congregation would build a second church in 1954). This church was dedicated on October 14, 1883. On this date the first sermon in English was delivered. Previously, all sermons had been in German. Through the years the Old Church was renovated and enlarged leading to a rededication service on March 16, 1924.
From 1928 to 1931 a rift developed between the congregation and Pastor Charles Strasen. The reasons for the dispute are somewhat vague, though it seems to have been more a matter of personalities than of theology. Although a reconciliation was attempted, Pastor Strasen on February 10, 1929 resigned and with a small number of followers formed St. Matthew's Lutheran Church. In April 1929, Edgar Hoenecke was called as pastor of St. Peter's. The split continued for two years, then in 1931 when it was announced that St. Matthew's might join the Missouri Synod, the congregation of St. Peter's, under the leadership of Pastor Hoenecke petitioned the presidents of both the Wisconsin and Missouri Synods of the Lutheran Church to work to settle the dispute. Reconciliation of the two congregations was effected November 5, 1931 with the passing of a resolution that followed a meeting between former pastor Strasen and members of St. Peter's.
Under Hoenecke's leadership the Christian Day School was built, dedicated and opened on September 7, 1947. A new church (referred to in the finding aid as "New Church") was erected. The cornerstone was laid October 31, 1954 and the New Church was dedicated on September 11, 1955. A new parsonage was constructed and ready for use on December 2, 1956. Additions to the Christian Day School were formally completed with a dedication service on December 7, 1975 under the guidance of Pastor Leonard Koeninger.
St. Peter's Evangelical Lutheran Church celebrated its 125th anniversary on March 8, 1981. It continues to be an active and thriving congregation.
The records of the St. Peter's Evangelical Church cover the period of 1856 to 1985 with the majority of the materials falling within the years of 1916 to 1960. The early records are in German, but most of the records from about 1920 are in English. The record group contains documents pertaining to the founding and history of the church, as well as its articles of association, bylaws, and constitution. Financial reports from 1939 to 1952, general correspondence, membership records, publications, announcement books, and records of the meetings of the Church Council and various committees from 1856 to 1961 are also included. There are photographs and pictures of the various pastors who have served the church over the years. Other audio/visual materials include slides, and cassette and reel-to-reel tapes.
The record group is arranged in ten series: Record Books, History, Operational, Buildings, Pastors, Congregation, Church Activities, Publications, Visual Materials, and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Lutheran Church--Michigan--Plymouth.; Church buildings--Michigan--Plymouth (Mich.)--Churches.; St. Peter's Evangelical Lutheran Church (Plymouth, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Berdan House (Plymouth, Mich.); Business enterprises.; Churches.; Classrooms.; General stores--Michigan--Plymouth.; Hotels and taverns.; Interiors--Churches.; Interiors--General stores.; Interiors--Michigan--Plymouth.; Kellogg Park (Plymouth, Mich.); Lutheran Church--Michigan--Plymouth.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Plymouth.; Church buildings--Michigan--Plymouth.; Streets--Michigan--Plymouth.; Plymouth Marble Works.; Schools--Michigan--Plymouth.; Tombs and sepulchral monuments.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Record Books
  The core of the record group is the church record books. These include minutes of congregational meetings and of the board of stewards. Also of interest here are sacramental registers and a log of daily church activities. The researcher should note that most of these records for the period before 1921-1922 are in German. A large part of this series that is in English are volumes containing announcements made from the pulpit each Sunday, and also a register of the record of hymns sung and the sermons delivered.
  - Congregational minute books
    - 1856-1884 (Box 1)
    - 1884-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1947 (Box 1)
  - Board of Stewardship minute books
    - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1967 (Box 1)
  - Pastoral conference minute book (?) 1899-1931 (Box 1)
  - Kirchen Buch (sacramental register ?) 1886-1911 (Box 1)
  - Protokollbuch (log of daily church events) 1877-1905 (Box 1)
  - Lutheran Ladies Aid minute book 1911-1946 (Box 1)
  - Account book 1886-1911 (Box 1)
  - Announcement books 1931-1960 (Box 2)
- History
  - Founding/Early years of congregation 1856, 1858, 1884 (Box 3)
  - Church Anniversaries (Box 3)
- Operational
  - Annual reports 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Articles of Association, bylaws, constitution (Box 3)
  - Finance 1941-1965 (Box 3)
  - Financial correspondence 1931-1976 (incomplete) (Box 3)
  - Annual non-profit reports 1939-1952 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence 1916-1954 (incomplete) (Box 3)
- Building
  - Old Church (Box 3)
  - New Church 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - New Church Dedication correspondence 1955 (Box 3)
  - Missouri Synod's land purchase 1954 (Box 3)
  - Christian Day School 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - School Addition 1973-1975 (Box 3)
- Pastors
  - Hoenecke, Edgar--Essay (Box 3)
  - Koeninger, Leonard--Anniversary brochures (Box 3)
  - Bunge, R.H.--Sermon books 1906-1911, 3 volumes (Box 3)
- Congregation
  The files of the Congregation series contain confirmation listings, letters of transfer, and baptismal records. Of particular interest is the documentation concerning the controversy within the church which occurred from 1928 to 1931 resulting in a split in the congregation and the formation of the short-lived St. Matthew's Lutheran Church. Many of the documents pertaining to the split are in German. The controversy was noteworthy as Pastor Strasen was issued a restraining order to prevent him from preaching. Newspaper clippings from this period delineate the facts of the quarrel.
  - Membership (Box 3)
  - Confirmation Listings 1910-1981 (Box 3)
  - Baptism Records 1955, 1957 and Letters of Transfer, 1930-1954 (incomplete) (Box 3)
  - St. Matthew's Congregation Controversy 1928-1931 (Box 3)
  - Voters' Assembly, Minutes 1967-1969 (incomplete) (Box 3)
  - Ladies Guild Yearbooks 1980, 1982, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Lutheran Ladies & Young Ladies' Society (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Church Activities
  - Christmas Fete 1955, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Sunday School, Minutes, Financial Reports, misc. (Box 3)
- Publications
  - Order of Service / Harvest Home 1937, November 1963-June 1964, 11/13/1977 (incomplete) (Box 3)
  - The Plymouth Lutheran 1932 (Box 3)
  - St. Peter's Messenger January 1969 (Box 3)
- Visual Material
  - Photographs
    - Plymouth, Michigan (Box 4)
    - Old Church (Box 4)
    - New Church (Box 4)
    - New Church dedication (Box 4)
    - Christian Day School, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - New school additions 1974 (work crews) (Box 4)
    - Pastors (Box 4)
    - Church groups (Box 4)
    - Church pageant (Box 4)
    - Christmas fete (Box 4)
    - Harvest Home (Box 4)
    - Parade Float (Box 4)
  - Slides
    - Founders Day Program, 125th Anniversary, 2 folders (Box 4)
      (script to accompany slides located in history file)
    - Church Picnic 1977, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Church and School 1978 (Box 4)
    - Pastor Berg's Farewell (Box 4)
    - Youth Group
      - Parade Float (Box 4)
      - Canoe Trip (Box 4)
- Sound Recordings
  - Reel-to-reel tapes
    - Farewell to Rev. and Mrs. Hoenecke January 1960, 3 3/4 ips (Box 4)
    - Pastor Berg's Farewell Dinner January 1968, 3 3/4 ips (Box 4)
    - Pastor Koeninger's 25th Anniversary sermon and anniversary party; also sermon delivered by Pastor Hoenecke upon occasion of the 25th Anniversary sermon of the Day School, four track monaural; 3 3/4 ips (Box 4)
  - Cassettes
    - Organ demonstration, early morning service May 1985 (Box 4)
    - Organ Dedication March 1985 (Box 4)
    - "In His word ... made free" (with slide) (Box 4)